MR. LIPSKÝ BONAPARTA
TN. LIPSKÝ BONAPARTA
Ruhenheim.
Ruhenheim.
There it is.
Ini tempatnya.
Stop it, Ludwig!
Hayo, Ludwig!
What on earth are you barking at?
Kau ini menggonggong ke siapa?
Has your bicycle broken again?
Sepedamu rusak lagi?
Yes. The chain keeps coming off.
Ya. Rantainya los terus.
I got it off the trash heap, so I guess it is trash.
Sepeda dari tempat pembuangan memang rongsok.
It doesn't look like trash to me.
Menurutku sepeda ini bukan rongsokan.
When I ride it, everyone says, "Look at the trash! He's riding trash!"
Saat kunaiki, semuanya bilang,
"The trash is riding trash!"
Rongsokan naik rongsokan!"
That's not true.
Itu tidak benar.
That's a magnificent five-speed super bicycle.
Ini sepeda hebat dengan lima kecepatan.
Let me see if we can fix this again.
Biar kucoba perbaiki lagi.
-You have a guest. -Who?
Sepertinya ada tamu.
Oh, right. He should be the one who called.
Oh. Dia pasti yang tadi menelepon.
Excuse me. Are you the guest with the reservation?
Permisi. Apa kau yang sudah pesan…
Yes. I'm Lunge.
Benar. Namaku Lunge.
Of course. Mr. Lunge, Welcome.
Ya, Pak Lunge. Selamat datang.
I called at the last minute, so I'm glad you have a room.
Pemesananku mepet sekali. Syukurlah masih ada kamar.
Not at all. We always have vacant rooms here.
Tidak masalah. Selalu ada kamar kosong di sini.
It's still the off-season, is it?
Karena bukan musim liburan, ya?
It's always the off-season here.
Di sini selalu sepi pengunjung.
Our only other guests right now are that couple over there.
Tamu kami yang lain cuma pasangan yang duduk di sana.
He can't use his legs, so any kind of trip is quite difficult.
Dia berkursi roda, jadi agak sulit bepergian.
I'll get his bag.
Biar kubawakan tasnya.
Thank you, Wim.
Tolong, ya, Wim.
-Take him to room 302. -Right.
- Antar dia ke kamar 302. - Siap.
How is the view from that room?
Bagaimana pemandangan dari kamar itu?
It has the best view in the hotel.
Pemandangan dari kamar itu paling indah di hotel ini.
I'll leave your bag here.
Tasnya kutaruh di sini, ya.
It doesn't look like trash to me either.
Bagiku sepeda itu juga bukan rongsokan.
I think it's a pretty nice bicycle.
Menurutku sepedamu bagus.
Inspector Lunge of the BKA?
Inspektur Lunge dari BKA?
What are you doing at a country substation like this?
Ada keperluan apa di polsek ini?
I was wondering how many more officers for backup you could get if you needed it?
Jika kalian butuh petugas tambahan, berapa banyak petugas yang siaga?
More officers? For backup?
Petugas tambahan? Untuk membantu?
If I call the state police,
Jika menghubungi kepolisian daerah,
I can get quite a lot in just under an hour.
banyak yang bisa datang dalam satu jam.
I doubt we'd ever need it in a backwater town like this.
Tapi kurasa itu tak diperlukan untuk kota terpencil seperti ini.
You should check out everyone who comes into town from now on.
Mulai sekarang, periksalah semua pendatang yang masuk kota ini.
What?
Apa?
Before anything terrible happens.
Sebelum terjadi bencana.
Nice! There we go! You're running well!
Bagus! Begini baru benar! Kayuhannya lancar.
Time to shift gears!
Saatnya pindah gigi!
Ow!
Aduh!
-What's wrong, trash? -You still riding that trash?
- Apa-apaan, Rongsokan? - Masih naik rongsokan itu?
What an ugly piece of junk!
Dasar sampah jelek!
Stop! Cut it out!
Hentikan!
Trash!
Dasar sampah!
Nice one!
Mantap!
Are you okay?
Kau tak apa?
Are you alone?
Kau sendirian?
Are you traveling alone?
Bepergian sendiri?
Yes.
Ya.
For work?
Urusan pekerjaan?
No. On my free time.
Bukan. Liburan.
My! Aren't you lonely traveling alone?
Wah. Apa tidak kesepian berlibur sendirian?
No. I'm used to it.
Tidak. Aku sudah terbiasa.
Do you have a family?
Kau sudah berkeluarga?
Yes, I do. I have a daughter and grandchild.
Ya, aku punya seorang putri dan cucu.
You have a grandchild, don't you?
Oh, kau sudah punya cucu.
Grandchildren are nice.
Cucu itu anugerah.
Ours is so very kind to us.
Cucu kami sangat menyayangi kami.
Look. I just wrote a postcard to our grandchild.
Lihat. Aku baru saja menulis kartu pos untuk cucu kami.
Letters are such a wonderful thing.
Surat itu luar biasa.
You can write things in a letter you just can't say face-to-face.
Hal yang tak bisa diungkap langsung bisa ditulis dalam bentuk surat.
Why not write one yourself?
Bagaimana jika kau juga menulis surat?
A letter to my grandchild?
Surat untuk cucuku?
I wonder what I should write.
Apa yang harus kutulis, ya?
Anything you like.
Apa pun boleh.
If only I could draw too.
Andai aku juga bisa menggambar.
Excuse me. Would it be possible to stay here for the night?
Halo, permisi. Bisa pesan satu kamar untuk semalam?
Yes, of course.
Ya, tentu saja.
I'm glad to hear it.
Wah, syukurlah.
I was having a leisurely picnic, but then I lost my way.
Aku tiba-tiba tersesat di jalan saat piknik santai.
When I finally made it to this town, it was so late.
Sesampai di kota ini, tiba-tiba sudah petang.
I'm glad you have a room.
Untung masih ada kamar.
It seems nobody else got off in this town.
Tampaknya tak ada yang turun di kota ini.
A gunshot?
Tembakan?
It didn't sound like a gunshot to me.
Aku tak dengar suara tembakan.
No, that sounded like a gunshot.
Tidak, aku yakin itu suara tembakan.
Nobody in this town owns a gun.
Tak ada yang punya pistol di kota ini.
The only one who probably does is that drunk who lives behind us.
Kalau ada, mungkin si pemabuk yang tinggal di belakang.
It would've been a lot louder if it were behind us.
Kalau sedekat itu, pasti letusannya lebih keras.
Besides, that alcoholic couldn't hit a thing.
Lagi pula, tukang mabuk itu tak mungkin bisa jitu.
Oh, darn it all! "Couldn't hit"?
Astaga. "Tak mungkin bisa jitu"?
Quit saying things like that! No wonder I always lose!
Gara-gara omongan macam itu, nomorku tak pernah tembus!
Darn it all!
Astaga.
Shut up! It's not my fault! Give up those stupid lottery tickets!
Berisik! Itu bukan salahku! Menyerahlah beli lotre konyol itu!
Ludwig!
Ludwig!
I can't find my Ludwig anywhere!
Ludwig tak ada di mana-mana!
You heard that gunshot earlier, didn't you?
Kau dengar suara tembakan tadi, 'kan?
Do you think it was my dear Ludwig? Was he shot?
Mungkinkah Ludwig tersayangku ditembak? Jangan-jangan…
Please calm down, Mrs. Hillman.
Tolong tenang, Bu Hillman.
There was no gunshot. Just calm down.
Tidak ada tembakan. Tenanglah.
Is there something wrong?
Apa ada masalah?
This woman's dog has gone missing.
Anjing Ibu ini hilang.
That's worrying.
Pasti dia cemas.
Anyway, I'll tell the police.
Baiklah, aku akan lapor polisi.
I already told the police!
Aku sudah lapor polisi!
But that man is useless!
Polisi itu tak berguna!
He's so undependable for a police officer!
Dia polisi yang tak bisa diandalkan!
It doesn't help that he hates dogs!
Apalagi, dia benci anjing!
How about I look for him?
Mau kubantu carikan?
Can you do that, Mr. Neumaier?
Kau tak keberatan, Pak Neumaier?
Sure. I'm going for a stroll around town, so I'll look while I'm out.
Tidak. Akan mau keliling kota, jadi kucarikan sekalian.
Yes, I know Mrs. Hillman's dog.
Ya, aku tahu anjing Bu Hillman.
It's that dumb dog that never stops barking, right?
Anjing bodoh yang suka menggonggong itu, 'kan?
It's gone missing. Have you seen it?
Anjingnya hilang. Kau melihatnya?
No, I haven't.
Tidak lihat.
I see. Thanks anyway.
Begitu. Terima kasih.
One more thing. Have you seen any odd strangers in this town lately?
Satu pertanyaan lagi. Apa kau melihat orang asing mencurigakan belakangan?
Yes, I have.
Ya, ada.
Really?
Sungguh?
You.
Kau orangnya.
A dog?
Anjing?
I thought you were here for a room.
Kukira kau mau pesan kamar.
I'm sorry. I'm already staying at the Versteck Hotel.
Maaf. Aku sudah menginap di Hotel Versteck.
That darn place steals all the visitors.
Hotel sialan itu merebut semua pengunjung.
So I guess that means you don't have any guests here now.
Berarti di hotel ini tak ada tamu.
No, I don't! It's as quiet as a cemetery here.
Tak ada! Hotel ini sepi sekali.
So I'd know in an instant if that noisy dog was anywhere near here.
Makanya, kalau anjing berisik itu di sekitar sini, aku pasti dengar.
Did you hear it barking today?
Apa kau dengar suara gonggongan hari ini?
No, I didn't.
Tidak dengar.
Earlier, there was that gunshot, right?
Jangan-jangan… Tadi ada suara tembakan, 'kan?
I bet some maniac shot and killed it because it was being too damn noisy.
Pasti ada orang gila menembaknya karena anjing itu terlalu berisik.
Hello… Mister?
Halo… Maaf?
I'm Lunge, Mr. Neumaier.
Aku Lunge, Pak Neumaier.
Right. Mr. Lunge. Where are you headed?
Pak Lunge, mau pergi ke mana?
I'm looking for that dog.
Aku mencari anjing itu.
I see. Have you gotten any leads?
Begitu. Sudah dapat petunjuk?
No.
Belum.
Then I guess we'd better keep looking.
Kalau begitu, mari kita terus mencari.
Liquor, dammit! Get me some liquor!
Alkohol! Belikan Ayah alkohol!
No, Dad! You shouldn't drink!
Jangan! Ayah tak boleh minum lagi!
Get out there and buy me some liquor, goddammit!
Sana keluar dan belikan alkohol!
I don't have any money!
Aku tak punya uang!
You have the money you made at your damn job!
Kau ada uang dari pekerjaan paruh waktumu itu, 'kan?
I guess maybe I can get one bottle.
Mungkin beli sebotol cukup.
Wim.
Wim.
Don't use it for that. That's money that you earned yourself.
Tak usah dibelikan. Itu hasil jerih payahmu sendiri.
You got beaten up pretty badly again today.
Kau dipukul habis-habisan lagi, ya?
Come on now to my hotel.
Ayo ikut ke hotelku.
MÜLLER GROCERY STORE
TOSERBA MÜLLER
This is great!
Enaknya!
Not many people around here enjoy them like you do.
Jarang-jarang ada yang selahap itu di sini.
Is that right? But this is just so darn good.
Benarkah? Tapi ini enak sekali.
Really? It's just a sausage.
Padahal cuma sosis biasa.
This is the face I make when I eat good food.
Ini ekspresiku saat menyantap makanan lezat.
This is a nice town. It's quiet and has delicious food.
Kota yang indah. Suasananya tenang, makanannya enak.
Do you think so?
Menurutmu begitu?
I want to get out of this dull town as soon as I can.
Aku ingin segera pergi dari kota membosankan ini.
I wish I can meet some handsome guy who would take me away from here.
Andai ada pria tampan yang menjemputku pergi dari sini.
Have any handsome guys been around lately?
Apa belakangan ada pria tampan?
Not at all.
Tidak ada.
I get the same customers every darn day. I'm sick of it.
Aku melayani pelanggan yang sama tiap hari. Aku muak.
By the way, about that dog…
Omong-omong, soal anjing itu…
Right. I've taken that dog for a walk myself.
Oh. Aku pernah mengajak anjing itu jalan-jalan.
You have?
Jalan-jalan?
When Mrs. Hillman was in bed with a cold,
Saat Bu Hillman sakit flu dan istirahat,
I took him for a walk for her.
kugantikan mengajaknya jalan-jalan.
When I gave him one of our deli's Eisbein bones,
Saat kuberi dia tulang dari Eisbein toko kami,
he wouldn't let go of it!
dia tak mau melepaskannya!
He pulled it out of my hand with incredible strength and ran off!
Tulangnya direbutnya dengan kasar, lalu dia kabur!
Where did he go then?
Dulu anjingnya lari ke mana?
Inspector Lunge.
Inspektur Lunge.
It's just as you've said, something terrible did happen.
Seperti katamu, bencana sungguh terjadi.
That dog, it's gone missing.
Ada anjing yang hilang.
Did you hear that gunshot?
Kau dengar suara tembakan tadi?
A car broke down on the state highway.
Ada mobil mogok di jalan tol kota.
I bet it was just that car backfiring.
Paling itu suara knalpot meletup.
We never hear gunshots in this town.
Belum pernah ada suara tembakan di kota ini.
See you.
Sampai jumpa.
You don't want to scare me like that, you know.
Bahaya kalau mengejutkanku seperti itu.
There he is.
Ketemu.
Ludwig.
Ludwig.
You sure have caused a lot of trouble.
Kau bikin orang khawatir.
You must have remembered you buried that bone here.
Kau pasti ingat pernah mengubur tulang itu di sini.
Hello, Mr. Lunge.
Halo, Pak Lunge.
I guess we both arrived at the same place from different leads.
Tampaknya kita tiba di tempat yang sama dari petunjuk yang berbeda.
What are you doing in this town?
Apa tujuanmu ke kota ini?
I could ask you the same thing. You're a police detective, right?
Tujuanmu sendiri apa? Kau penyidik, 'kan?
I could kind of tell.
Aku bisa menebak.
You have the aura of a detective.
Kau punya aura detektif.
I'm on vacation.
Aku sedang berlibur.
From that look in your eyes, it sure doesn't seem like you're on vacation.
Dari tatapanmu, kau tak seperti sedang berlibur.
I was just in Prague not long ago.
Aku baru saja dari Praha.
I got info there on a certain person involved in a certain case.
Ada informasi mengenai seseorang yang terlibat dengan suatu kasus.
He's a tall man carrying a large bag.
Seorang pria tinggi yang menjinjing tas besar.
He's friendly and has a gentle smile.
Dia ramah dan senyumannya lembut.
His hair color is…
Dan warna rambutnya…
You're an exact match with the information I have on the man,
Kau sama persis dengan deskripsi di dataku soal orang itu,
Mr. Neumaier.
Pak Neumaier.
I mean, Mr. Grimmer.
Bukan. Maksudku, Pak Grimmer.
What have you come to this town for?
Untuk apa kau datang ke kota ini?
It does seem like you and I
Tampaknya kita berdua benar-benar
both arrived at the same place through different leads.
sampai di tempat yang sama dengan petunjuk yang berbeda.
Isn't that right?
Benar, 'kan?
Do you think it can be stopped?
Apa menurutmu bisa dihentikan?
The horrible massacre that will happen in this town.
Pembantaian mengerikan yang akan terjadi di kota ini.
Are you checking the lottery numbers again?
Hei, kau mengecek nomor lotre lagi?
Your husband's about to go to work to pay for that.
Padahal suamimu akan kerja membayar hobimu itu.
You talk big, but you earn a pittance.
Gaji kecil, tapi sombong.
What?
Apa?
We have no future unless we win the lottery.
Masa depan kita suram kalau tak menang lotre.
If you don't like it, then earn more.
Kalau tak suka, cari uang yang banyak.
Honey!
Sayang!
Oh, what is it now?
Berisik, ada apa lagi?
What is it, dammit?
Ada apa memangnya?
We won!
Menang…
Won what?
Menang apa?
The lottery!
Lotre!
Give it back!
Kembalikan!
What did you do with my bicycle?
Kalian apakan sepedaku?
Get lost!
Berisik!
We don't know about any bicycles.
Kami tak tahu soal sepedamu.
But we did toss out some trash.
Kalau rongsokan, kami membuangnya.
Did you toss it out?
Kalian membuangnya?
We tossed it into the vampire's house in the west hills.
Ya. Kami membuangnya ke rumah vampir di bukit barat.
The vampire…
Rumah vampir…
If you want it back, go get it yourself.
Kalau butuh rongsokan itu, ambil saja sendiri.
But don't blame us if you don't come back.
Tapi tanggung sendiri akibatnya.
You piece of trash!
Dasar sampah!
Honey…
Sayang…
Did anyone come by?
Apa ada yang datang?
No…
Tidak…
Make sure you chain the door.
Pastikan pintunya dirantai.
So…
Hei.
Yes?
Ya?
Are you sure the numbers are a match?
Kau yakin angkanya sama, 'kan?
I've checked several times.
Sudah kuperiksa berulang kali.
We… did win.
Kita benar-benar menang lotre.
Twenty million marks, huh?
Dua puluh juta mark, ya?
What will we do, honey?
Kita harus bagaimana, Sayang?
I went to the next town.
Tadi aku pergi ke kota sebelah.
Honey, what are these?
Sayang, apa ini?
Just a precaution.
Untuk berjaga-jaga.
With all that money, it's too dangerous to be unarmed.
Menang uang sebanyak itu, bahaya kalau tak bersenjata.
But as long as nobody finds out, we won't need to use these.
Tapi selama tak ada yang tahu, pistol ini tak perlu digunakan.
But…
Soal itu…
What is it now?
Ada apa lagi?
There isn't anyone who knows what numbers you chose, is there?
Tak ada yang tahu nomor lotremu, 'kan?
When I bought that lottery ticket…
Sebenarnya, saat aku membeli tiket lotre itu…
The usual.
Beli lotre.
Here you go.
Silakan.
You never seem to win, do you, Mrs. Heinich?
Kau tak pernah menang, ya, Bu Heinich?
Hello, Mr. Conrad.
Halo, Pak Conrad.
Your husband complains about your obsession with the lottery.
Suamimu mengeluhkan obsesimu dengan lotre.
Why don't you try using my birthday? March 2, 1945.
Coba pakai tanggal ulang tahunku. 2 Maret 1945.
Those numbers won quite a bit.
Nomor itu cukup sering menang.
I've won two long shots at the horse races with them.
Dua kali aku menang besar di pacuan kuda pakai nomor itu.
Yeah, yeah. Maybe sometime.
Ya. Mungkin kapan-kapan.
Don't tell me… you used the birthday of that Conrad?
Jangan bilang, kau memakai tanggal ulang tahun Conrad?
Yes…
Ya…
If he sees the numbers in the paper…
Kalau dia melihat nomor itu di koran…
But he doesn't know if you bet on those numbers, right?
Tapi dia tak tahu kau memakai nomor itu untuk lotre, 'kan?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
Rumors could be spreading through town by now--
Bisa saja rumornya sudah menyebar di kota.
Come to think of it…
Aku jadi ingat…
What is it?
Ada apa?
On my way home just now,
Dalam perjalanan pulang tadi,
when I stopped by the store for cigarettes…
aku mampir ke toko untuk membeli rokok.
The girl from the sausage shop was staring at me.
Gadis di toko sosis itu terus menatapku.
That's right! The same thing happened to me!
Benar juga! Aku juga mengalaminya.
When I took out the trash just now,
Saat aku membuang sampah tadi,
the drunk out back was there staring at me!
pemabuk di belakang rumah terus menatapku!
If that alcoholic hears about us winning all this money, he might--
Jika tukang mabuk itu tahu kita menang besar, dia bisa…
-Calm down! -But!
- Tenang! - Tapi…
Listen. We'll just have to protect ourselves.
Dengar. Yang penting, kita bisa melindungi diri sendiri.
The vampire's house…
Rumah vampir…
It's dead…
Kucingnya mati…
Someone is here.
Ada orang di sini.
Judging from the look of things…
Dilihat dari keadaan ruangan ini…
He hasn't been here recently.
Tampaknya dia sudah lama tak kemari.
None of them are finished.
Tak ada lukisan yang selesai.
Did he stop painting?
Apa dia berhenti melukis?
Or maybe he couldn't paint anymore.
Atau mungkin dia tak bisa melukis lagi.
Mr. Neumaier. Mr. Lunge.
Pak Neumaier. Pak Lunge.
What are you doing here?
Sedang apa kau di sini?
My bicycle…
Itu… Sepedaku…
My friends said they tossed out my bicycle here.
Teman-temanku bilang sepedaku dibuang ke sini.
Your friends pulled a trick on you?
Teman-temanmu iseng, ya?
Your bicycle was in the bushes at the bottom of the trail up here.
Sepedamu ada di semak-semak di kaki bukit.
Anyway…
Omong-omong,
It looks like that cat was killed with a submachine gun.
tampaknya kucing tadi dibunuh dengan pistol mitraliur.
Are they already here?
Mereka sudah tiba?
Yes. They're very close.
Ya. Mereka sudah di sini.
Look at this.
Lihat ini.
-A drawing of twins. -Correct.
- Lukisan anak kembar. - Benar.
This one is too.
Yang ini juga.
And this one.
Ini juga.
-There must be about ten. -What?
Sekitar sepuluh lukisan.
When I got the Tenma case, those twins were about ten years old.
Saat aku menyelidiki kasus Tenma, si kembar berusia sekitar sepuluh tahun.
It looks like it was drawn about then.
Sepertinya lukisan ini digambar pada masa itu.
How many times has he drawn the same picture?
Berapa kali dia melukis subjek yang sama?
No matter how many times he draws them, he's not satisfied.
Berapa kali pun melukisnya, dia tak pernah puas.
Good grief.
Astaga.
Looks like there will be lots of creeping vines this year.
Sepertinya tahun ini tanaman rambat merajalela.
We might not be getting many lingonberries this year.
Bisa-bisa tahun ini tak bisa panen lingonberi.
Say, I've never seen you around here before.
Kau orang baru di sini, ya?